You know, I am so bad at tech
أتعلمون انا سيء جدا عندما يتعلق الأمر بالتكنولوجيا
that my daughter -- who is now 41 --
قالت ابنتي .. والتي هي ابنة 41 عام الآن
when she was five, was overheard by me
عندما كانت في الخامسة من عمرها .. والذي سمعته صدفة
to say to a friend of hers,
قالت لاحدى صديقاتها
If it doesn't bleed when you cut it,
ان كان الامر لا ينزف منه الدماء
my daddy doesn't understand it.
فان والدي لن يفهمه - لأنه جراح -
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, the assignment I've been given
لذا فالمهمة التي اوكلت لي
may be an insuperable obstacle for me,
تبدو مهمة عويصة بالفعل
but I'm certainly going to try.
ولكني سوف احاول ان
What have I heard
الخص ما سمعته من مؤتمر تيد
during these last four days?
في الايام الاربعة الماضية
This is my third visit to TED.
هذه هي زيارتي الثالثة لمؤتمر تيد
One was to TEDMED, and one, as you've heard,
الاولى كانت لمؤتمر تيد الطبي .. واعتقد انكم سمعتوا حديثي هناك
was a regular TED two years ago.
والثانية كانت لمؤتمر تيد الاعتيادي منذ سنتين
I've heard what I consider an extraordinary thing
ان الذي سمعته اليوم .. اعتقد انه امرٌ فريد من نوعه
that I've only heard a little bit in the two previous TEDs,
وهو شيء لم المسه في المؤتمرين الماضيين
and what that is is an interweaving
وقد لمست الجدل
and an interlarding, an intermixing,
والتنوع .. والاختلاط
of a sense of social responsibility
بين الحس الاجتماعي والافكار التي تطرح
in so many of the talks --
في معظم الاحاديث التي طرحت في المؤتمر
global responsibility, in fact,
ربما يمكن القول انه حس اجتماعي عالمي - ان صح التعبير -
appealing to enlightened self-interest,
يهدف الى تنوير النفس
but it goes far beyond enlightened self-interest.
وينطلق الى ابعد من ذلك .. ابعد من تنوير النفس
One of the most impressive things
وواحدة من الامور المدهشة التي لمستها
about what some, perhaps 10,
عند ما يقارب 10 متحدثين
of the speakers have been talking about
اثناء تحدثهم عن اختصاصاتهم
is the realization, as you listen to them carefully, that they're not saying:
هو الواقعية .. فعندما تستمع اليهم جيدا . تراهم لا يقولون
Well, this is what we should do; this is what I would like you to do.
حسنا .. هذا الذي يجب القيام به .. او هذا الذي ارغب بالقيام به
It's: This is what I have done
بل .. هذا ما قمت به
because I'm excited by it,
لانني مهووس بذلك .. او مهتم .. نصير لتلك القضية
because it's a wonderful thing, and it's done something for me
لانها امرٌ رائع .. وقد غيرتني تلك - الفكرة , القضية -
and, of course, it's accomplished a great deal.
وحتما سينتج عن هذا - الفكر - حديثُ رائع وممتع
It's the old concept, the real Greek concept,
ان المفاهيم القديمة .. مفاهيم الاغريق
of philanthropy in its original sense:
عن الفيلانثروبي .. في نصوصها الاصلية
phil-anthropy, the love of humankind.
الفيلانثروبي تعني حب البشر
And the only explanation I can have
والتفسير الذي رأيت عن ذلك الامر
for some of what you've been hearing in the last four days
من الامور التي استمعت لها في الايام الاربعة الماضية
is that it arises, in fact, out of a form of love.
هو نفسه .. ذلك العمل الذي يصدر عن النفس بدافع الحب
And this gives me enormous hope.
وذلك العمل الذي يدفع في انفسنا الامل الكبير
And hope, of course, is the topic
والامل .. هو الموضوع الذي أريد ان اتحدث عنه اليوم
that I'm supposed to be speaking about,
وهذا الموضوع الذي يتوجب علي التحدث عنه
which I'd completely forgotten about until I arrived.
كنت قد نسيته تماما حتى وصلت الى هنا
And when I did, I thought,
وعندما وصلت .. فكرت
well, I'd better look this word up in the dictionary.
ان انظر الى القاموس لعلي اجد بعض التعاريف المتعلقة بالامل
So, Sarah and I -- my wife -- walked over to the public library,
لذا قمت انا وسارة - زوجتي - بالذهاب الى المكتبة العامة
which is four blocks away, on Pacific Street, and we got the OED,
والتي تبعد اربعة قطاعات سكنية عن هنا .. في شارع المحيط
and we looked in there, and there are 14 definitions of hope,
وقد نظرنا هناك ووجدنا 14 تعريف للأمل
none of which really hits you
ولا واحد منهم مقنع صراحةً
between the eyes as being the appropriate one.
بحيث تشعر انه ملائم فعلا لذلك المفهوم - الامل -
And, of course, that makes sense,
وحتما هذا امرٌ منطقي
because hope is an abstract phenomenon; it's an abstract idea,
فالامل هو ظاهرة مجردة .. فكرة مجردة
it's not a concrete word.
انها ليست كلمة مبسطة او واضحة او معرفة
Well, it reminds me a little bit of surgery.
ويذكرني هذا قليلا بالجراحة
If there's one operation for a disease, you know it works.
فالمرض الذي له طريقة جراحية واحدة .. تكون عادة ناجحة
If there are 15 operations, you know that none of them work.
ولكن ان كان هنالك 15 طريقة جراحية لذلك المرض .. فعليك ان تعلم ان ولا واحدة منها ناجحة
And that's the way it is with definitions of words.
وهكذا هي الامور مع الكلمات وتعريفها
If you have appendicitis, they take your appendix out, and you're cured.
فاذا كنت تعاني من الزائدة الدودية .. يمكننا بكل بساطة ازالتها .. وتكون بذلك قد شفيت
If you've got reflux oesophagitis, there are 15 procedures,
ولكن اذا كنت مصاب بتخلخل بفتحة المريء .. فهنالك 15 طريقة لتلافي ذلك
and Joe Schmo does it one way
يعتمد الدكتور " جو سكمو " طريقة
and Will Blow does it another way,
والدكتور " ويل بلو " طريقة اخرى
and none of them work, and that's the way it is with this word, hope.
وفي الواقع لا تنفع اي من تلك الطرق .. وهكذا هو الامر مع كلمة " الأمل "
They all come down to the idea of an expectation
فتلك التعاريف جميعا تصب في خانة " التوقعات "
of something good that is due to happen.
توقع شيء جيد سوف يحدث
And you know what I found out?
واتعلمون مالذي وجدته ايضا
The Indo-European root of the word hope
وجدت جذر الكلمة " الهندو اوروبي " لكلمة الامل
is a stem, K-E-U --
انها " كيه - ايه - يو "
we would spell it K-E-U; it's pronounced koy --
انها تلفظ " كي اي يو " ولكنها حقيقية تلفظ " كوي "
and it is the same root from which the word curve comes from.
وهذا الجذر اللغوي هو نفس جذر كلمة منعطف
But what it means in the original Indo-European
ولكن ماذا يعني هذا في اللغة الهندو اوروبية
is a change in direction, going in a different way.
انه يعني التغير في الاتجاه .. والانتقال الى منحى جديد
And I find that very interesting and very provocative,
وقد وجدت ذلك امرا مثيرا للاهتمام والفضول
because what you've been hearing in the last couple of days
لان هذا ما كنا نسمعه في الايام الماضية
is the sense of going in different directions:
اي تغير الحياة والاتجاه والافكار
directions that are specific and unique to problems.
لان الوجهات التي نعتمد هي مشاكل فريدة .. ومميزة
There are different paradigms.
وهنالك عدة مقاربات -نماذج- لاعتماد الوجهة المطلوبة
You've heard that word several times in the last four days,
وكلمة - نماذج - هي كلمة سمعناها مرارا في الايام الماضية
and everyone's familiar with Kuhnian paradigms.
وخاصة عندما جرى التحدث عن نماذج " كوهينيان "
So, when we think of hope now,
أي عندما نفكر بالأمل الآن
we have to think of looking in other directions
علينا ان نفكر بالنظر في وجهات جديدة
than we have been looking.
غير تلك التي ننظر اليها الآن
There's another -- not definition, but description, of hope
وهناك وصف للامل - وليس تعريف له -
that has always appealed to me, and it was one by Václav Havel
كان دوما يخطر في بالي قيل من قبل " فاكولف هافيل "
in his perfectly spectacular book "Breaking the Peace,"
في كتابه الرائع " اختراق السلام "
in which he says that hope
والذي يقول فيه ان الأمل
does not consist of the expectation that things will
ليس ان تجري الامور كما نريدها ان تكون
come out exactly right,
انما هو
but the expectation that they will make sense
ان تكون الامور منطقية لنا في النهاية
regardless of how they come out.
مهما كانت تلك النتائج
I can't tell you how reassured I was
ولا يمكنني ان اخبركم كم كنت مطمئنا
by the very last sentence
لتلك الجملة الاخيرة
in that glorious presentation by Dean Kamen a few days ago.
في العرض الرائع الذي قام به " دين كامين " منذ عدة ايام
I wasn't sure I heard it right,
ولست متاكدا ان كنت قد سمعت بالضبط ما اظن انني سمعته
so I found him in one of the inter-sessions.
فوجدته بعد المؤتمر في الاجتماعات الجانبية
He was talking to a very large man, but I didn't care.
وكان يتحدث الى رجل ضخم الجثة .. ولم اكترث لذلك
I interrupted, and I said, "Did you say this?"
فقطاعت حديثهما .. وسئلته " هل قلت هذا ؟ "
He said, "I think so."
قال " نعم اظن ذلك ! "
So, here's what it is: I'll repeat it.
وهذا كان الذي قاله .. ساكرره لكم
"The world will not be saved by the Internet."
" ان العالم لن يتم انقاذه بواسطة الانترنت
It's wonderful. Do you know what the world will be saved by?
هذا امرٌ رائع .. هل تعلمون مالذي سينقذ العالم
I'll tell you. It'll be saved by the human spirit.
سوف اخبركم .. قال .. ان الذي سينقذ العالم هي الروح البشرية
And by the human spirit, I don't mean anything divine,
وبواسطة الروح البشرية لا اعني اي شيء " روحاني "
I don't mean anything supernatural --
ولا اقصد حدوث معجزات .. او خوارق
certainly not coming from this skeptic.
فانا حتما لا أؤمن بهكذا امور
What I mean is this ability
ولكن اعني بهذا . .القدرة
that each of us has
التي يملكها كل واحد منا
to be something greater than herself or himself;
بان يصبح شيئاً أفضل مما هو عليه الآن
to arise out of our ordinary selves and achieve something
لكي يرتقي بنفسه .. ويحققَ شيئاً
that at the beginning we thought perhaps we were not capable of.
شيء كنا نظن في البداية انه غير ممكن
On an elemental level, we have all felt
وعندما نضع انفسنا جميعا في نفس السوية .. فنحن جميعا نشعر ..
that spirituality at the time of childbirth.
بتلك الطاقة ربما أثناء ولادة طفل ما
Some of you have felt it in laboratories;
او داخل مختبرات الابحاث
some of you have felt it at the workbench.
او في ورشات العمل
We feel it at concerts.
واحيانا نشعر بتلك الطاقة في الحفلات الموسيقية
I've felt it in the operating room, at the bedside.
بالنسبة لي انا اشعر بها داخل غرفة العمليات .. وفي غرف الانتظار
It is an elevation of us beyond ourselves.
انها تلك الطاقة التي ترفعنا لكي نصل مستويات جديدة
And I think that it's going to be, in time,
وجميعنا سنشعر بتلك الطاقة يوما ما
the elements of the human spirit that we've been hearing about
ان الاشخاص الذين كنا نستمع اليهم هنا في هذا المؤتمر
bit by bit by bit from so many of the speakers in the last few days.
كلمة . .بكلمة .. همسة بهمسة .. من العديد من الذين تحدثوا في الايام الماضية
And if there's anything that has permeated this room,
فان الذي تخلل احاديثهم وانتشر عبر هذه القاعة
it is precisely that.
هي تحديدا تلك الطاقة
I'm intrigued by
التي انا مفتون بها تماما
a concept that was brought to life
ذلك المفهوم الذي ظهر
in the early part of the 19th century --
في بداية القرن التاسع عشر
actually, in the second decade of the 19th century --
وتحديدا في نهاية العقد الثاني منه
by a 27-year-old poet
بواسطة شاعر عمره 27 عاما
whose name was Percy Shelley.
كان اسمه " بيرسي شيلي "
Now, we all think that Shelley
قد يخطر على بالكم الآن ان شيلي
obviously is the great romantic poet that he was;
هو شاعر رومانسي كبير .. وهو كذلك
many of us tend to forget that he wrote
ولكن من يعرفونه عادة يتناسون
some perfectly wonderful essays, too,
انه كان يكتب مقالات رائعة جدا
and the most well-remembered essay
وأكثر المقالات التي نتذكرها بشدة..
is one called "A Defence of Poetry."
تدعى " دفاعا عن الشعر "
Now, it's about five, six, seven, eight pages long,
وهي عبارة عن مقالة من 5-6 صفحات
and it gets kind of deep and difficult after about the third page,
وتصبح معقدة وعميقة بعد الصفحة الثالثة
but somewhere on the second page
ولكن في الصفحة الثانية
he begins talking about the notion
يتحدث فيها عن مفهوم
that he calls "moral imagination."
يسميه " المخيلة الاخلاقية "
And here's what he says, roughly translated:
وفي تلك الصفحة يقول .. وهذه ترجمة سريعة لها
A man -- generic man --
" الرجل - الرجل الحقيقي
a man, to be greatly good,
الرجل " الكبير " الرائع
must imagine clearly.
يجب ان يتخيل بصورة واضحة
He must see himself and the world
نفسه .. والعالم
through the eyes of another,
من خلال أعين شخص آخر
and of many others.
بل عدة أشخاص آخرون
See himself and the world -- not just the world, but see himself.
لكي يرى العالم بمنظور آخر .. ليس العالم فحسب بل هو أيضاً
What is it that is expected of us
اذا ما المتوقع منا ؟
by the billions of people
من قبل المليارات حول العالم ؟
who live in what Laurie Garrett the other day
الذين يعيشون فيما وصفه " لاري جاريت " ذاك اليوم
so appropriately called
بصورة دقيقة
despair and disparity?
بالاحباط واليأس
What is it that they have every right
ماذا من حقهم ان
to ask of us?
يطلبوا منا نحن ؟
What is it that we have every right to ask of ourselves,
ومالذي يجب ان نطلبه نحن من انفسنا
out of our shared humanity and out of the human spirit?
من منظور تشاركنا الانساني .. ومن مفهوم الروح الانسانية المشتركة
Well, you know precisely what it is.
حسنا .. اتعلمون ماذا هو هذا الشيء تحديدا
There's a great deal of argument
قد يكون هنالك جدل
about whether we, as the great nation that we are,
يخصنا نحن ... على اعتبارنا امة كبيرة
should be the policeman of the world,
عن حول انه يجب ان نلعب دور .. شرطي العالم .. وضابط امنه
the world's constabulary,
وحامي اصقاعه
but there should be virtually no argument
ولكن لا يجب ان يكون هنالك اي جدل
about whether we should be the world's healer.
عن دورنا في شفاء ورفع الانسان سوية معيشته حول العالم
There has certainly been no argument about that
ولاشك قد كان هنالك جدلٌ حول هذا
in this room in the past four days.
في هذه القاعة منذ عدة ايام
So, if we are to be the world's healer,
إذاً، إن كنا نريد لعب دور " طبيب هذا العالم "
every disadvantaged person in this world --
كل مريض في هذا العالم
including in the United States -- becomes our patient.
وضمنهم مرضى الولايات المتحدة يصبحون مرض في إطار مسئوليتنا
Every disadvantaged nation, and perhaps our own nation,
وكل دولة في حالة عوّز .. او ربما في دولتنا
becomes our patient.
تصبح مسئوليتنا نحن
So, it's fun to think about the etymology of the word "patient."
ومن الممتع ان ننظر الى جذور كلمة " مريض "
It comes initially from the Latin patior, to endure, or to suffer.
فهي تأتي من الجذر اللاتيني .. الذي يعني " معاناة " او " عوز - نقص "
So, you go back to the old Indo-European root again,
وعندما نعود الى الجذر الهندو اوروبي مرة اخرى
and what do you find? The Indo-European stem is pronounced payen --
نجد ان كلمة مريض تلفظ " باين "
we would spell it P-A-E-N -- and, lo and behold, mirabile dictu,
ونحن نلفظها " بي إيه إي إن " ولا اعتقد انه من قبيل المصادفة
it is the same root as the word compassion comes from, P-A-E-N.
ان ذلك الجذر اللغوي هو نفسه الجذر اللغولي لكملة " تراحم "
So, the lesson is very clear. The lesson is that our patient --
واعتقد ان هذا الدرس مهم جدا .. هذا يعني " ان المريض خاصتنا " - مسئوليتنا -
the world, and the disadvantaged of the world --
حول العالم .. او النقص في سوية المعيشة حول العالم
that patient deserves our compassion.
يجب ان تنال منا التعاطف والتراحم والتفهم
But beyond our compassion, and far greater than compassion,
واكثر من التعاطف .. واعظم منه
is our moral imagination
هو مخيلتنا الاخلاقية
and our identification with each individual
وتعريفنا الشخصي لذواتنا ..
who lives in that world,
نحن الذين نعيش في هذا العالم
not to think of them as a huge forest,
حيث لا يجب ان ننظر الى انفسنا وكأننا غابات
but as individual trees.
بل نحن أشار منفردة في تلك الغابة الكبيرة " العالم "
Of course, in this day and age, the trick is not to let each tree
وحتما في هذا اليوم .. وفي هذا العصر .. يتوجب ان لا ندع اي شجرة
be obscured by that Bush in Washington that can get --
تنصاع او يشوش تفكيرها من قبل " بوش " في واشنطن .. قدر المستطاع
can get in the way.
لكي لا يخرب علينا تلك المفاهيم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, here we are.
لذا ها نحن
We are, should be,
وهكذا يجب ان نكون
morally committed to
ملتزمين أخلاقيا
being the healer of the world.
لن نكون مرشد العالم وحاميه
And we have had examples over and over and over again --
ولدينا عدة امثلة على هذا .. كثيرة جدا
you've just heard one in the last 15 minutes --
سمعنا بعضاً منها منذ 15 دقيقة
of people who have not only had that commitment,
عن اشخاص لم يلتزموا فحسب بواجباتهم
but had the charisma, the brilliance --
بل هم يملكون الكاريزما .. والتألق والذكاء
and I think in this room it's easy to use the word brilliant, my God --
واعتقد وبما اننا في هذا المؤتمر فمن السهل القول انهم لامعون ومبدعون واذكياء
the brilliance to succeed at least at the beginning
ذلك الذكاء الذي قادهم من بداية مشوارهم
of their quest,
في ذلك الالتزام
and who no doubt will continue to succeed,
والذي بدون اي شك سوف يستمر معهم حتى النجاح
as long as more and more of us enlist ourselves in their cause.
طالما اننا لا نتصرف بأنانية .. ونهتم بقضايا الآخرين
Now, if we're talking
وان كنا نريد التحدث ...
about medicine,
عن الادوية
and we're talking about healing,
بينما نحن نتحدث عن الشفاء والعناية
I'd like to quote someone who hasn't been quoted.
فأنا اريد ان اقتبس من شخص لم يُقتبس منه من قبل
It seems to me everybody in the world's been quoted here:
رغم انني أرى ان الجميع " يقتبس من الجميع "
Pogo's been quoted;
فبوغو تم الاقتباس عنه
Shakespeare's been quoted backwards, forwards, inside out.
وشكسبير تم الاقتباس عنه مراراو تكرار
I would like to quote one of my own household gods.
ولكني اريد اليوم ان اقتبس من من اعتبره احد الاسرة الإلهية
I suspect he never really said this,
رغم اني اشك انه قال ذلك
because we don't know what Hippocrates really said,
لانني لا نعرف تحديدا مالذي قاله أبقراط
but we do know for sure that one of the great Greek physicians
ولكننا نعلم انه كان حتما واحد من الاطباء الاغريق القدامى
said the following,
وقد قال التالي
and it has been recorded in one of the books attributed to Hippocrates,
وقد قرأتها في احد الكتب المنسوبة اليه " ابقراط "
and the book is called "Precepts."
وذلك الكتاب يدعى " التعاليم "
And I'll read you what it is.
وسوف اقرا لكم
Remember, I have been talking about,
تذكروا ما كنت اتحدث عنه من قبل
essentially philanthropy:
" العمل الخيري "
the love of humankind, the individual humankind
و حب الانسانية .. حب الاشخاص
and the individual humankind
حب الافراد
that can bring that kind of love
ذلك الحب الذي يدفع الاشخاص
translated into action,
لتحويله الى عمل
translated, in some cases, into enlightened self-interest.
وتحويله الى قضية ... قضية شخصية .. قضية سامية
And here he is, 2,400 years ago:
وهذا ما قيل منذ 2400 سنة
"Where there is love of humankind,
" عندما نحب البشر
there is love of healing."
حينها سنحب ان نداويهم من امراضهم "
We have seen that here today
وقد رأينا هذا في هذا المؤتمر
with the sense,
بكل منطق
with the sensitivity --
وبكل حساسية
and in the last three days,
في الايام الثلاث الماضية
and with the power of the indomitable human spirit.
وبواسطة القوة التي لا تقهر . .قوة الروح البشرية
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)